Guide to the Jesse Chickering Papers, 1805-1919
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Jesse Chickering papers 1805-1919
Chickering, Jesse, 1797-1855
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library Durham, North Carolina 27708-0185
RL.00222
Language: English.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. The library may require up to 48 hours to retrieve these materials for research use.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Biographical Note
Jesse Chickering, 1797-1855, was an author and political economist.
Collection Overview
Contains journals, correspondence, financial papers, writings and speeches, and printed materials. Most material concerns Chickering's career as author and political economist. The Writings and Speeches Series contains the manuscript drafts of Chickering's writings, including his Statistical View of the Population of Massachusetts from 1765 to 1840 (1846); Emigration into the United States (1848); Reports on the Census of Boston (1851); and Letter addressed to the President of the United States on Slavery, considered in Relation to the Principles of Constitutional Government in Great Britain and in the United States (1855). Other subjects in this series include constellations, bank reports from several Boston banks, Harvard alumni, and publication of Chickering's work.
The Correspondence Series includes personal letters and letters pertaining to research on Massachusetts population growth. Correspondents include: Levi Woodbury, George Ticknor, John Langdon Sibley, David Henshaw, George Bancroft, Henry I. Bowditch, Horace Mann, Daniel Webster, and James Buchanan (Harvard Librarian). Immigration, slavery, and Harvard University are also mentioned in the correspondence. The Journals Series contains statistical information on immigration into the United States between 1819 and 1855, with emphasis on Massachusetts. The Miscellaneous Series includes information pertaining to astronomy, including cloth maps with astronomical models and planetaria.
Subject Headings
Woodbury, Levi, 1789-1851; Ticknor, George, 1791-1871; Sibley, John Langdon, 1804-1885; Henshaw, David, 1791-1852; Bancroft, George, 1800-1891; Bowditch, Henry I (Henry Ingersoll), 1808-1892; Webster, Daniel, 1782-1852; Mann, Horace, 1796-1859; Astronomical models; Planetaria; Slavery -- Law and legislation; Constellations; Harvard University -- Alumni; Immigrants -- United States -- Massachusetts; Massachusetts -- Population; Banks and banking, American -- Massachusetts -- Boston
Contents of Collection
- Journal Series
  - 1819-1871, (5 folders) (Box 1)
- Correspondence Series
  - 1821-1858, (8 folders) (Box 2)
- Financial Papers Series
  - 1859, undated, (2 folders) (Box 3)
- Writings and Speeches Series
  - Astronomical, 1827-1828, undated (Box 3)
  - Banks, undated (Box 3)
  - Bank Dividend Report, 1841, undated (Box 3)
  - Constitution and Government, 1758-1780, undated (Box 3)
  - Convents and Catholicism, 1794-1835, undated (Box 3)
  - Harvard Alumni, 1852, undated, (2 folders) (Box 3)
  - Immigration into the United States, 1847-1851, undated, (2 folders) (Box 3)
  - Legislative Representation, 1853, undated (Box 4)
  - Market Bank Report, 1835-1841, undated (Box 4)
  - Medical, 1835, undated (Box 4)
  - North and City Bank Reports, 1841-1845, undated (Box 4)
  - On the Declaration of Independence, undated (Box 4)
  - Population, 1830, undated (Box 4)
  - Reports on the Census of Boston, 1851, undated (Box 4)
  - Slavery:
    - Nebraska Question, 1854 (Box 4)
    - North American Review, Slavery and the Missouri Question, 1820 (Box 4)
    - Slavery in the United States Constitutionally Considered, undated (Box 4)
  - Statistical View of the Population of Massachusetts from 1765-1840 (Box 4)
  - Wealth in Mass., undated (Box 4)
  - Miscellaneous, 1821-1851, undated, (2 folders) (Box 4)
- Printed Materials Series, 1826-1855 and undated, (5 folders)
  - Constitution and by-laws of the American Statistical Association (Box 5)
  - Influence of slavery upon the white population (Box 5)
  - The United States Constitution. (Box 5)
  - Letter addressed to the President of the United States on slavery (Box 5)
  - Nouvelles idées sur la population (Box 5)
  - Address of the Hon. Edward Everett, at the anniversary of the American Colonization Society, January (Box 5)
  - Colonization. (Box 5)
  - The history of Charlestown, Massachusetts (Box 5)
  - Does slavery Christianize the negro? (Box 5)
  - The "ruin" of Jamaica (Box 5)
  - The inter-state slave trade. (Box 5)
  - American steam navigation. (Box 5)
  - White slavery in the United States. (Box 5)
  - Tables showing the number of emigrants and recaptured Africans sent to the colony of Liberia (Box 5)
  - Anti-slavery tracts (Box 5)
- Miscellaneous Series
  - General, 1821-1864, undated (Box 5)
  - Astronomical studies, undated (Box 5)
  - Clippings, 1854-1851, undated (Box 5)
  - Legal papers, 1805-1860, undated (Box 6)
  - Railroads, 1836-1843, undated, (2 folders) (Box 6)
- Oversize Materials
  - Writings and Speeches Series
    - Statistical View of the Population of Massachusetts from 1765-1840. undated (Box 7)
  - Printed Material Series
    - 1838-1918, undated (Box 7)
  - Miscellaneous Series
    - Astronomical studies, undated, (2 folders) (Box 7)
    - General, undated (Opaperfolder 1)
    - Miscellaneous, 1821-1864 and undated (Opaperfolder 2)